<engine>
	<action selector="#content">
		<p>
			The term
			<i>
				<b>open source</b>
			</i> describes practices in production and development that promote access to the end product's source materials. Some consider open source a philosophy, others consider it a
			<a title="Pragmatism" href="/wiki/Pragmatism">pragmatic methodology</a>. Before the term
			<i>open source</i> became widely adopted, developers and producers used a variety of phrases to describe the concept;
			<i>open source</i> gained hold with the rise of the
			<a title="Internet" href="/wiki/Internet">Internet</a>, and the attendant need for massive retooling of the computing
			<a title="Source code" href="/wiki/Source_code">source code</a>. Opening the source code enabled a self-enhancing diversity of production models, communication paths, and interactive communities.
			<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-0">
				<a href="#cite_note-0">
					<span>[</span>1
					<span>]</span>
				</a>
			</sup> Subsequently, the new phrase "
			<a title="Open-source software" href="/wiki/Open-source_software">open-source software</a>" was born to describe the environment that the new
			<a title="Copyright" href="/wiki/Copyright">copyright</a>,
			<a class="mw-redirect" title="Licensing" href="/wiki/Licensing">licensing</a>,
			<a title="Domain name" href="/wiki/Domain_name">domain</a>, and consumer issues created.
		</p>
		<p>
			The open-source model includes the concept of concurrent yet different agendas and differing approaches in production, in contrast with more centralized models of
			<a title="Software developer" href="/wiki/Software_developer">development</a> such as those typically used in commercial software companies.
			<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-1">
				<a href="#cite_note-1">
					<span>[</span>2
					<span>]</span>
				</a>
			</sup> A main principle and practice of open-source software development is
			<a title="Peer production" href="/wiki/Peer_production">peer production</a> by bartering and collaboration, with the end-product, source-material, "
			<a class="mw-redirect" title="Blueprints" href="/wiki/Blueprints">blueprints</a>," and documentation available at no cost to the public. This is increasingly being applied in other fields of endeavor, such as
			<a title="Biotechnology" href="/wiki/Biotechnology">biotechnology</a>.
			<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-2">
				<a href="#cite_note-2">
					<span>[</span>3
					<span>]</span>
				</a>
			</sup>
		</p>
	</action>
</engine>
